A Guide to the Walter H. Ryland Briefs, 1968-2003
Washington and Lee University, School of Law, Lewis F. Powell, Jr. Archives
Lewis F. Powell, Jr. Archives, School of Law, Washington and Lee University
Walter H. Ryland Briefs, 1960-1999
Lewis F. Powell, Jr. Archives, School of Law, Washington and Lee University
018
4 cubic feet.
Walter H. Ryland
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Walter H. Ryland.
Biographical Information
Walter H. "Rusty" Ryland was born in Richmond, Virginia on January 23, 1943, and raised in Urbanna, Virginia. He graduated from Washington and Lee University in 1965 and from its School of Law in 1967.
He practiced at a Richmond firm for a short time before joining the Virginia Attorney General's Office in 1968. He spent fifteen years in state practice which led to frequent appearances in federal court. After three years as university counsel at what is now Virginia Tech University, he returned to the Attorney General's Office as head of the Education Section. Eventually he was elevated to Chief Deputy to the Attorney General.
In 1983, Ryland went into private practice with the Richmond firm Williams Mullen from which he retired in 2008. He lives in Richmond and practices part-time.
Scope and Content
The Walter H. Ryland Briefs consist of four record cartons containing bound records and briefs from Ryland's legal career. There is also on volume of transcriptions of education law conferences in which Ryland participated.
Contents List
- Briefs in Chronological Order 1968-2003 (Carton 1-2)
- Briefs by Case 1975-2001 (Carton 1-2)
  - Adarand Constructors v. Pena (and Mineta in three iterations, 1994-2001 (Carton 2)
  - Northeastern Florida Chapter of Associated General Contractors v. City of Jacksonville, 1992 (Carton 2)
  - Michigan Road Builders v. Director of the Michigan Department of Transportation, 2001 (Carton 2)
  - City of Richmond v. J.A. Cronson Company (and J.A. Cronson Company) v. City of Richmond), 1985-1988 (Carton 3)
  - Cramer v. Virginia Commonwealth University, 1976-1979 (Carton 3)
  - Kruse v. Campbell 1976-1978 (Carton 3)
  - Maximus, Inc. v. Lockheed Information Management Systems, 1997-2000 (Carton 3)
  - Maryland Highway Contractors Association, Inc. v. State of Maryland, 1997-1991 (Carton 4)
  - Richmond Newspapers, Inc. v. Commonwealth of Virginia, 1980 (Carton 4)
  - The Supreme Court of Virginia v. Consumers Union of the United States, 1975-1981 (Carton 4)